so this is a
magikarp 82
and it's a i'll just read out this
discussion that's happening between
venerable ratapada and a
certain king at the time
and this king describes four kinds of
lust that a person can go through and then on
that a person can go through and then on
account of that
would ordain as a monk
go forth
as a holy man
[Music] he points out that venable rattapada has
he points out that venable rattapada has
not experienced those losses so why has
he ordained
[Music] and he replies i went forth
and he replies i went forth
because he understood these four
summaries of the dhamma taught by the
buddha what were the four lawsuits oh
the four
the four losses
that the king says
people go forth for is a loss of youth
when they're old
they've got nothing more to do they they
they they
loss of health they get sick
loss of wealth and loss of relatives
[Music] so and uh
and uh
but uh bengal ratzapada describes these
why he went forth
on account of these four summaries of
dhamma number one is
number one is
life in any world is unstable
which kind of relates to that aging you
know things are aging
things are aging
things are falling apart
well yeah but i mean unstable in a sense
yeah you don't need to
your old age is not guaranteed
you might not live that long
so as you said so many times before
i don't know from what book that quote
is but
as soon as you're born you're old enough
to die i think i think it was quoting it
from somebody else very very correctly
the point is yeah as soon as there is a
manifestation implication of death is there at any
implication of death is there at any
given time
the implication of cessation
so
whether you're 10 20 60 year old doesn't
matter that implication is there
and if somebody becomes aware of that
you realize oh yeah no that is the
reality so life is unstable
so life is unstable
so that whole hindu idea of
uh four stages of life whereby the only
last stage is when you go forward and
that's how you get most of the whole
life it's completely based on these
assumptions that you will reach the
old age and that your faculties will be
working in the old age and you won't be
kind of affected by illness and so on
it's just basically a worldly idea of
trying to squeeze as much as they can
out of sensuality and then go and
practice their holy life failing to
understand that the longer you stay
not practicing the holy life the more
of a burden you accumulate
so if you were not able
to go against the grain and give up the
burden when there wasn't so much burden
accumulated you're not going to be able to do it
you're not going to be able to do it
when you're 60 with like you know a lot
of burden
in your mind of and i mean burden in
terms of like you know attachments
habits views
views
assumptions control sense of mastery
sense of mind all of that proliferates
it's not a static thing
habits the habits yeah
ferment proliferation yeah even these
small mundane habits are quite a lot for
people but let alone you know the ones
that your kind of life depends on
so
understanding that life is unstable
in itself is more than enough to try and
do something about it if you truly
understand the weight
of that
instability yeah that that aging is already you
yeah that that aging is already you
ready well exactly yeah yeah aging is
not when you turn 60 aging is already
this and so you are already aging and
and so you are already aging and
you are already heading towards that
disintegration of the aggregates and uh
it it's not guaranteed that you're gonna
see the you know 80 90 year old age or
something
because manifestations there means
possibility of death is there but it
feels like i am yeah i'm a good guy
exactly so i want to live a long way
using feelings
instead of
discernment is a very perilous game
is a very perilous game
yes so
putting off these things that you you
know i need to sort this out
i need to sort this out
later i'll do it later let me get the
most out of this
yeah and that's
well that's that's smarter talking
and this second
summary of the dharma
that he heard is a life in any world has
no shelter and no protector
that seems to relate to the illness
yeah yeah well safety
that's like you know in the winter
comparison like you should
not allow your consciousness to rest
upon anything as as a as a safe
safe space safe place because it isn't
the only safe place is complete
cessation and dispassion and abandoning
of everything this life everything
everything humanity humanity
love attachments
things that are due to you all of that
is a trap
so
that's what it was actually teaching
very different from what people think to
what i was teaching you know
world peace and loving kindness and so
on one mind is safe yeah nothing nothing
is safe like compared
what does it compare consciousness to
the the
whip like being hit with a whip
with the spears
yeah the spears yeah the contact was a
whip similarly
similarly
yeah so each time your consciousness
gets established upon something you
should regard it as being struck with a
spear because that's the peril of it
because that's the peril of it
so there's truly nothing to regard
to regard
as as
suitable to rest upon
no safety no safety the only safety is
that cessation of ownership
complete removal of this passion
and pretty much any appreciation of life
or anything within it it needs to be
abandoned so disenchantment revulsion all those
so disenchantment revulsion all those
things that would ever describe it
so you can you can yeah try and be so
the mind turns away
and completely lets go of any
need for safety
because need for safety is based on the
wrong assumptions it's based on the
sense of ownership sensory and sense of
mind thus the need to protect what's
mine need to find a safe space for what's
need to find a safe space for what's
mine
where it would be safe
but see
so for as long as you're seeking some
safety you're implying some ownership
of something you want to be safe
and thus you you won't be safe because
of that very thing
it vulnerability yeah yeah exactly
[Music] so you are vulnerable
so you are vulnerable
because you take things
well you take things they're not yours
as yours
so you're in debt you're vulnerable
mara has access to you
and the third
summary life in any world has nothing of
its own
one has to leave all and pass on
so yeah accumulation of wealth
well well honestly pretty much or very
kind have you ever gained it really yeah
exactly have you ever secured it well
like again even like oh this is mine
remember i think we spoke about a while
ago in one of the talks like even the
notion of things that belong to you you
don't need to start you know breaking
them with a hammer to prove that you're
not the owner just start just make the
effort and understand
what do you mean
do you mean
like for yourself when you say oh this
item this is my
this belongs to me
what does it belonging entail
like how does it feel in a way like what
is it
as a phenomena that
belonging of something to you
does that mean you're in its control
does that mean you're its creator does
that mean you it cannot be taken away
what does that ownership imply
and you realize that that's the trick of
the ownership is
the power of the ownership is the the
people don't think about it you just
kind of skate on the top on top of it
take it for granted oh my mind mind my
mind but even without any buddhist
practice if a mind would just stop and
think about
like what does it mean when something is
mine like how would i describe that
what are the properties of that
and then you realize the contradiction
in terms
and certainly it would help you
not take
things that are yours so much as yours
they wouldn't be as much yours let's say
like that because you realize well yeah
the notion of mine it's quite relative
it's mine for as long as that thing is
there but i have no fundamental say in that or
but i have no fundamental say in that or
it's mine for as long as i'm there but i
have no fundamental saying that
so then okay it's relatively mine
as in i am the current user of it
but people people don't but by not
thinking about that
what does mine mean
uh they do take it in that kind of
infinite sense
that's why always that infinite threat
of when something mind is threatened to
be taken away even if you stop and think
about it actually i don't care much
about it but i care that mine is
attacked that mind is under a threat
because i never question the notion of
mine and i take it in an infinite sense
ultimate sense that mind means mind
forever and must stay be protected that
way and that's even like again
and that's even like again
even
further contradiction
because if it were yours you wouldn't
need to protect it
if it were your income in your control
it would not be under any threat it
could not be under a threat
if you were the master of its existence
he will listen only to you
but none of that's the case yet people
go around
with the attitude mind belongs to me
and that's how you can only it's the way
you know
that's what passion is you know you
can't have
passion for something if it's not really
yours yeah exactly exactly doesn't
really matter it's gone yeah
well that's yeah if you start
questioning that notion of mine
you you are already narrowing down i
suppose you could say
the basis for proliferation of passion
so you are diminishing passion that in
simple terms
by questioning the notion of mind you
are diminishing passion and you you you
you will be
not unlikely to be
unlikely to be
trying to get things
yeah yeah yeah or not as much driving or
not not
not yeah exactly not be um
[Music] as gripped by that kind of blind
as gripped by that kind of blind
ambition without any context
of its ultimate relativity like and
relativity i mean exactly yeah yeah i
work for it i earned it it's mine i
built it i created it that still doesn't
mean that it cannot be taken away and
that it won't be taken away so what
manual rutabala says is fundamentally
from that ultimate point of view of you
know life and death pretty much yeah
nothing can be taken away nothing can be
taken with you everything will be taken
away you can then we then
you yeah you're able to reevaluate your
investments yeah exactly yeah yeah
because you're not acting out of this
assumption that you will live forever
and your possessions will carry on even
after you die or something my legacy and
stuff like that
that that becomes inconceivable
certainly inconceivable as a motivator
for action and
you know and provider of ambition that
that won't be possible because ambition
and action of that kind it's basically
always has to be rooted in passion
it makes things easier
i'm only here for a little while
do i need to have
all these requisites
you know do i do i have to have the
the most exquisite house
yeah if if the context is sustained then
life becomes easier but sustaining the
context is what's not easy
or building it up that's what's not easy
because it's not natural
it's not natural to go against the grain
of ownership and passion
so if you invest the effort to develop
wisdom and that context
then your life will be much easier why
because you will be
less able to suffer
because you don't have so much passion
in your mind that binds you to things
gratuitously so when they change you
will not be affected that's the
definition of peace
yeah all that stress that a person goes
to
for protecting the wealthy you know all
that insurance health insurance health
[Music]
because the mind doesn't know anything
other than the ownership of the senses
of the body and everything else that has
proliferated through that
my house my family my friend my
reputation my name my my business my
savings my this medic medicine my all
this burden
yeah exactly all of that is burdened
exactly all of that is burdened
while it's falling apart you're trying
to keep it yeah yeah but it's falling
apart beyond
[Music] and the fourth summary
and the fourth summary
life in any world is incomplete
insatiable the slave of craving
yeah there is no there's no satisfaction
really [Music]
[Music]
it's just appeasing the hungry animal
you can only
sort of
suppress the hunger until it comes back
and that cannot end
on on that level
so hunger cannot end simply by providing
food for it
it's a constant consumption so
exactly so the
point of the craving in life is not
the satisfaction it's perpetuation of
itself not the satisfaction of itself
so the hunger perpetuates itself through
eating because you ate you get hungry again
because you ate you get hungry again
and then you eat and then you get hungry
again and there is no other
nature there is not the reality to that
there is not the reality to that
so same goes with the thirst of craving
the tanha
it's there is no because it's a mental
attitude towards scratching the edge but it's the
towards scratching the edge but it's the
attitude that determines the
you know the desire the craving the
insufficient i want this i don't want
that itching itself
itching itself
doesn't neither need scratching nor not
scratching it's just an itch
hunger in itself does not need food
it's just hunger it's just discomfort
but the mental attitude
that sees the outcome of food as
pleasurable is what's dependent on that
is what's dependent on that
is what gives meaning to the hunger and
keeps acting out of it
so same with the craving
until you see
feeling for what it is
painful feeling as painful feeling
nothing more nothing less
agreeable feeling as agreeable feeling
nothing more nothing less a neutral
feeling has neutral feeling nothing more
nothing less the attitude of mind
effectively claiming will be
adding meaning to that through that
further assumption further need further
pressure further thirst and hunger
and that is
in itself
like a vicious circle that perpetrates
yourself infinitely that's why the life
in itself in any realm whatever else
wherever else it is
it's completely
insatiable because in itself it just
because in itself it just
provides a fuel for itself in terms of
craving basically in
when unpleasant feeling is present stop
trying to get rid of it
because that's how you provide fuel for
it
when the pleasant feeling is present
stop acting out of it for more of it
because that's how you provide fuel for
that craving
for more of it
and that because yeah pleasant feeling
is just pleasant exactly in itself
doesn't matter how dressing how pressing
an edge might be
the pressing side of an edge is your
mental attitude in itself itch is an
itch it does not need a stretch already
it's enough already yeah it does not
need a scratch
so that's why it's meant like for
another hand in the scene there's just
the scene in the heart there's just a
herd and so on you could even say in the
felt that's just felt
and perceived is just perceived there's
nothing else
because there are no more gratuitous
assumptions in regard to that so any
so any
mental pleasure
or pain
that arises on its own in itself is
enough there's never enough for me well exactly
there's never enough for me well exactly
it's never enough for the mind that's
taking it as mine
that carries the assumption of more or
less more if it's pleasurable the
assumption of more immediate
when pleasure is present the assumption
of more of it is immediately there
when pain is present the assumption of
less is immediately there and that's why
it will never be enough so that's why
you're interfering with it and that's
why you provide fuel inadvertently and
that's why it's insatiable
it's insatiable because you created the
notion of
satiability you remove the notion of satiability it
you remove the notion of satiability it
says it's completely
enough in itself
it's not insatiable anymore
it never was so you're so
it's an idea that i
if i go after these feelings
i try to see going after these feelings
already implies they're somehow not
enough yeah or they're somehow too much
i'm looking forward and that's your
assumption that's not the feeling but
that's your craving
and to what end for i want completion
yeah that's always kind of that kind of
that's always kind of that kind of
assumption yeah i want to feel whole but
failing to understand that you are the
one creating the division to begin with
by acting out
i want a few years stable yeah if you
don't act out
if you do allow ownership to dissipate
and kind of evaporate
so if you truly experience letting go of
things then things are already sufficient
then things are already sufficient
in the scene there's just a scene
that's it a whole picture
there is nothing to be insatiable there
and the only thing that there was
insatiable there was your own attitude
basically that you projected onto things
being insufficient
but it was just your attitude
gratuitously resisting organically
welcoming those feelings that presented themselves
those feelings that presented themselves
and thus made them insufficient and made
them insatiable